(upbeat music)
- Welcome to Web3 with A16Z Crypto,
your guide to the future of the internet.
I'm Robert Hackett.
Today's episode is a special one.
It's a roundtable on some of the most compelling ideas
at the intersection of AI and crypto,
sourced from members of the A16Z crypto team.
Today, you're gonna hear from builders, researchers,
and deal makers who are all wrestling with the big question,
how will these two powerful technologies collide,
and what happens when they do?
First, deal partner Sam Broner makes the case
for giving AI agents universal identities.
Then, research partners Scott Comyners
presents how crypto can provide AI
with levels and layers of rich context.
You'll also hear from deal partners Liz Harkaby
on AI monetization models.
Cara Wu on the next evolution of web crawlers.
Jay Drain on Proving Personhood online.
And finally, security engineer Matt Gleason
on how crypto turns internet advertising models on their head.
This is a tour of big fresh ideas
that hint at what an internet of the near future
could look like.
For the full list of ideas,
check out our recent AI crypto crossovers package,
which you can find at a16zcrypto.com.
As a reminder, none of the content should be taken
as investment, business, legal, or tax advice.
Please see a16z.com/disclosures
for more important information,
including a link to a list of our investments.
(upbeat music)
All right Sam, so your contribution
to this AI and crypto's use cases piece
was that agents should have universal identity.
What do you mean by that?
I think that when you go to a traditional application,
you go to the website or you go to the app on your phone,
you log in and you see your stuff there.
But what happens when you're working with an agent
that might show up in its own app,
but also on Slack or on a phone call over email, over text,
it gets a lot harder to know when you're interacting
with an agent with the right context
and right capabilities that you're authorized against.
And so a universal identity for agents
is a way of expressing this.
Like a unique, uniform resource identifier,
but it's not really rich enough.
And so like, how do you do payments?
How do you list capabilities?
How do you share a state?
And so we start to make this point
in longer strokes in that piece.
So talk to me, talk to me about why this is important.
Why does it matter that an agent
should have an identity of its own?
Agent state is not quite like traditional app state.
You wanna talk to a certain model, a certain LLM,
you wanna talk to a certain context,
what does the agent know about you?
You wanna talk to a certain set of capabilities.
And all that wrapped together
is what we think of as an agent.
And I think that to connect with an agent like that,
you're gonna need to be able to identify in a way
that is richer than with websites.
Let me give you an example.
So if you wanna book a hotel today,
you might go to a kayak.com or some other aggregator.
But what if you wanna book a whole trip
and you wanna do it with an agent?
Well, you might text the agent and say,
find me a nice hotel in Paris.
You might go to the agent's website
to look at pictures of the agent
and you might call the agent.
And for each of these three interactions,
ideally you're talking to the same agent
that remembers all of the rest of the context before.
You could even imagine a situation where you're
in another app, like you're maybe on your workplace slack,
maybe you're sitting in a third party application
looking at like food recommendations
and you wanna bring that same agent into the context.
That's a really rich interaction
and you need a way of universally identifying
and then locating that agent
so you can bring it into whatever context you're working in
even though you talk to it in multiple places.
So just to make this really concrete for people,
you're giving this example of booking a hotel,
booking a trip, but you're literally in Paris right now
sitting in a hotel room that you booked.
And before we got on this call,
you were talking to our producer
about food recommendations in the city.
So this is a very real problem
that you are navigating right now.
- Okay, well, I wanna go on to get a nice dinner
with a good friend tomorrow night.
But I will say, like I have the good fortune
to have a person that I can talk to
to help me book this restaurant.
And I'll tell you what my experience is with them.
I'm sending them links.
I've talked to them on the phone.
I've talked to them in person, obviously.
And I've got, you know, I've got Google's reservation window
that I can look at.
But I'm sort of keeping track of all this information myself
and the person that I work with, this assistant,
you know, I know all the places I can contact them.
And for our agents, we probably need a similar thing.
We need a way of contacting them on any platform
and sharing contacts with them
while understanding their capabilities.
And so for friends, I know their capabilities are like
when they're awake and sort of if they're by their laptop
or by their phone, 'cause they'll tell me all that.
But for agents, we don't yet have a good way
of expressing a set of capabilities like that.
What do they have access to?
What do they know about me?
Are they sleep deprived like I am right now?
'Cause I got off a Red Eye last night.
And you might want to have an identity system
that supports that kind of richer information.
- So you talk in your contribution about how Amazon
uses identifiers, it uses its own sort of spin on SKUs
to identify products on their site.
And then in that way to tag their sort of like digital
representation to the real world.
What is it about crypto that improves what we already have?
- Most marketplaces have identity as one of the core
building blocks of identifying market participants.
So you go on Amazon and you see these different SKUs.
Apple gives each app in the App Store, an ID on Facebook.
You have an identifier that says who you are.
But they don't expose those very well.
It's a little hard to pull that out
and use it in another context.
We talk about this a lot with Farcaster,
which is a crypto native social network
where you can export your identity and use it in other
places because it's built on blockchain rails.
And so for agents, one of the beautiful things about them
is that you can talk to them in multiple channels
and with multiple contexts, it would be such a shame
if agents got an identity from just one aggregator
from one extractive network and then couldn't bring
that identity to other places.
'Cause I want to be able to talk to my agent on the phone
by email in this app and in that app.
And so I guess, yes, we have any other places
that we don't have the type of rich identity
that we need for agents in a way that's available anywhere,
anytime without the risk of someone being able
to take it away from the agent.
I'll add one more thing, which is like,
the agents, I'm sort of an anthropomorphizing them.
Really, I'm talking about the entrepreneurs,
like an entrepreneur builds an agent.
And this is a new form of an application.
It's something that you can use and have be useful to you.
And I don't want entrepreneurs to be beholden
to a extractive marketplace,
which is like the only place their agents can live
when clearly agents deserve to live anywhere.
That's a core thing to think through,
is how do we make sure this identity is available
for anyone to build on top of?
- So really, what I'm understanding here is,
it's not just that the agent should have identity.
It's really this concept of universality
that is important.
You want that agent not to just be tied
to one particular service and potentially aligned
with their interests over whoever else is.
You want an agent that is universally identifiable
across all different services and can be used across them.
- Yeah, that's right.
I mean, the universal identity for agents,
sometimes people call it more like a passport.
You want the identity to be there,
but you also want to know a little bit about the agent.
And maybe you want to be able to stamp
every time you interact with it.
So you want to say it's a little bit richer than DNS,
which is the domain name service,
which is what underlies URLs and websites,
because you want it to be stateful
and you might want to be able to do payments over it.
But this rich universal identity can be built on blockchains
and I think likely should be because it guarantees
that it'll be permissionlessly composable,
it'll be credibly neutral.
It'll be accessible from anywhere
in a way that traditional systems don't guarantee.
- And by the way, while this is all happening
in the agent space,
I think Apple just enabled passports digitally on iPhones.
So you've got meet space in one direction
coming online and agents coming in with passports
on the other side.
- Yeah, so let's just talk about the first side.
So Apple is letting you host your passport in Apple.
And that's like very good.
But it happens because the government is saying,
all US citizens can have a passport.
It's sort of like how Apple is required
to load websites on the phone.
Like there is this resource that everyone has
and can use and Apple is picking it up.
And I'd like to see a similar thing for agents
where you have a universal identity
that people are using to describe agents
and Apple, Google, meta all refer to that same identity
instead of them building their own in-house
and forcing agent developers to do complicated things
to bridge the agents' characteristics across platforms
or even worse being stuck within one platform
and having sort of a toll booth as you try to leave.
- So you're pointing out that in the Apple context,
it's really a top-down kind of situation
and maybe you would be looking more
for this bottoms-up kind of thing
where you could have agents get identity
from all different sorts of places
and carry that wherever.
- Yeah, that's right.
And we're so early that we have the opportunity.
It's path dependent.
Like there's a lot of ways agent identity could go.
And right now because we're at a crossroads,
I think we should try to make an identity
that works well for the entrepreneurs
that are building agents long-term.
- Okay, well, thanks for joining us, Sam.
- All right, go, thanks.
- Okay, so Scott, you had a number of contributions
to this list.
You described four of your ideas
as having to do with context.
And the fifth one, which we'll get to afterward,
you said has to do with guardrails.
So let's talk about the first four
and how they can all be lumped together
with this idea of context in relation to AI.
- So just very quickly, like there are many different senses
in which AI changes how much we need context
and the types of context we need in our digital spaces.
So for example, perhaps the simplest,
everybody who has ever opened up chat GPT or CLAWD
or any of these personal use AI systems
has probably had the experience of having to re-teach
the AI a bunch of stuff that you thought it knew about you
because you had some interaction with it
where you said, I code everything in Python,
please give me this code in Python
or I really, really, really like this particular football team
or something, please tell me about this football team
or this is the type of math I'm trying to learn,
any of these sorts of things.
The second you open a new shell, it's typically gone.
This is such an issue that we're actually seeing
beginnings of marketplaces in stable context,
prompts that can cue the AI to do a specific thing
or bots that you can rent that have specific contextual frames
that sort of save you the trouble of teaching it
how to draw anime characters or something like that.
But all of that should be able to persist
and blockchains are a great tool for that
and perhaps the unique tool that allows you
to own your context, guarantee that it's interoperable,
you can take it from platform to platform
and guarantee that it's forward compatible
that even the AI's that haven't been built yet today
will be able to interact with it and interpret it.
>> This is such a cool idea.
What you're describing right now is that the status quo in AI
is you have like the world's nicest, most eager butler
except the butler has amnesia.
Like constantly forgets things that are important
about your relationship.
>> Exactly.
>> And the thing that blockchains can bring to the equation
is if they have one thing, they have memory.
Like they are a database, they can keep state,
they have storage, indefinitely, well into the future
and are, they're hard to manipulate as well.
So you can be sure that that data is non-corrupted
and accessible and has integrity, all of that good stuff.
>> And that you have control.
>> And that you have control of the data
and where it's used.
And eventually when we get there,
enough ability to permission which application see
which parts of it, then you can choose your contextual frame
when you enter into an application.
>> You know, one question that I have about this
is despite blockchains being great at memory,
you know, someone might counter that.
Yeah, but they're not as efficient.
Well, I was gonna say they're kind of inefficient databases.
You know, they are really like,
do you need a database of that capacity?
You know, that sort of like global
and has memory persist forever?
Like do you need to go whole hog in that direction?
Or can you use like something quicker or more efficient?
>> Yeah, great question.
So I mean, so you may not want this stuff to persist forever.
And indeed, it could maybe drift
or you could instruct it on when it decays
or something of the sort.
And certainly it's gonna need to be updateable, right?
Maybe you are really into Python
and then you discover scheme and you're like,
oh my gosh, why was I not always coding and scheme?
And so you need to like modify the context frame
that you're carrying with you.
But it's really important
if we're gonna have sort of an individually controlled
context system, that system has to be interoperable
and it has to be sort of accessible
to any AI application that gets created,
even ones that don't exist yet, right?
It has to have sort of a public API
that is standardized and forwards compatible, right?
It can be adapted for any system that comes out
rather than just sort of being built
for the form factor of whatever exists today.
And blockchains are basically the only technology
we have that does this, that allows you to commit
to interoperability and that creates everything
within a framework of public standards
that are forwards compatible.
So let's dip into each of these ideas
and how they relate to context.
Okay, let me just jump right from where we were
to prove a personhood.
Jay and I wrote a piece about proof of personhood
and the takeaway there is that forwards compatibility
and commitment to interoperability are essential
for any sort of individual identifier, right?
Just like your driver's license,
you need to be able to present it to anybody
who can verify that it's a driver's license
and say this is my proof of ID.
And you need to, for example, be able to present it
to a restaurant to prove your age maybe,
even if the restaurant was not built
when you got your driver's license.
That's forward compatibility.
So for the exact same reasons you need this
for your context, you're gonna carry it
from application to application,
you need this for your identifiers,
your proof of humanity and your proof of who you are.
Got it, okay, so that's the first case.
You also wrote a piece with Sam Bronner
about vibe coding and making sure that software
that you create on a whim or whatever can stay up to date
and doesn't get broken.
Exactly, so there's a stack of context hierarchy here.
So we were first talking about your personal context
for your interaction with applications.
The second one is global context about you.
So you control your contextual information
to every other application about who you are and so forth.
But also when you're vibe coding
or otherwise using AI to build software,
the feature of this technology is enabling people
to write custom workflows and code,
even if they've never studied programming before
or may not even know exactly what the system's doing, right?
They're appealing to an AI to do all the library extensions
and connections and things further to produce the thing they want.
That's a huge feature.
That's the superpower of AI coding.
But it has the challenge that you're introducing
two types of entropy.
You're both building entropy into your programs.
You're sort of adding things into your programs
that you yourself may not understand
and that the AI may not entirely understand.
It added them in because they sort of predicted
that they should go there and they might work,
but it might be that neither you nor the AI knows why.
And you're introducing entropy relative to everybody else.
You might have a program that fills out billing slips
and your colleague might have a program
that fills out billing slips that you both vibe code it up
and they're totally different from each other
and they're producing output that doesn't interoperate
with whoever in the billing department
is processing the billing slips.
They wrote their own vibe coded workflow
and it doesn't work with yours.
And so what Sam and I describe are what we call synchrony layers,
basically like protocol layers that get wrapped
and sort of like we have with software libraries today,
but software libraries are updated very infrequently, right?
A software library, you know, you put out the next release
and then maybe people suggest things
over a six to 12 month period
and then you get another release maybe.
Here what we need are fully dynamic layers
that both establish boundaries and updates
within Europe software and, you know,
standardizations across different peoples vibe coded software
so that you can be sure that you haven't somehow absorbed
a malicious code and so that other people can be sure
that they can work with what you're creating and vice versa.
And so that's like shared context.
We started with individual personal context,
individual global context.
This is like individual but shared context.
- Have you vibe coded anything, Scott?
- Oh, absolutely.
I've most recently been using this to create various forms
of puzzles in the form of fully on chain SVGs
and other sort of image structures,
but I've also used it in my research
in a bunch of different ways, right?
Oh, okay, but the real triumph?
Here's a great example, by the way.
Here's a place where I have no idea how this worked.
There is this conference, it's the top conference,
the intersections of economics and computer science.
And every year when you have a paper accepted,
you have to format the abstract or the paper
in a particular way.
And this year we had to make a very subtle
and complicated modification to the formatting package.
There was something wrong with the way it was printing
the co-authors of the paper's name line, basically.
And this thing is in unreadable code.
And so we vibe coded a script to fix this code
to do what we wanted it to do.
And like, it was magical, but for example,
we then had to take this product, right?
We took our final source code and shipped it to the publisher.
The publisher has the original version of the library,
not ours, and so when they sent us back the page proof
or whatever, we're going to have to check to make sure
that they didn't break this thing that we fixed.
And that's a place where a synchrony layer would be useful.
Like if they have reference to the fact
that we've made this change, the library file,
then we could be confident that they wouldn't recompile
our abstract and get something different.
- I don't know if this is directly applicable,
but I vibe coded myself a habit tracking app.
And what would be very cool is if I could have friends
of mine have their own instances of the app
so we could track our streaks and compete against one another.
- Oh my gosh, let me have that.
- But yeah, it would be helpful to have
that kind of shared state that we can all rely on.
- Exactly.
And this again, shared state.
The second you say shared state,
blockchain suddenly makes sense, right?
Like you're like, here's an instance
where you're trying to share information.
You're trying to create sort of like a local shared state
among a bunch of individuals.
And that's exactly what blockchains are good at.
So then the last step of the hierarchy,
and sometimes the most global is when you actually
have to establish global context.
Here we're talking about registries.
And you can think registry of deeds,
you can think registry of membership
in a, I don't know, famous fancy society or something.
Like, and in the roundup,
I wrote about registry of intellectual property.
And the registry of intellectual property
is particularly important as creative generative AI
is leading to this explosion of remixes and transformations.
And the internet has put pressure on intellectual property
since inception, but it's putting more pressure
on intellectual property at a very accelerating pace
than we've ever seen from digital technology before.
And the funny thing about it is it could be a feature.
Like there are all sorts of business models
and we're starting to see people experimenting
with business models around remixing and licensing
as the primary structure for creative IP.
But the existing intellectual property systems,
especially in the United States, aren't configured
in such a way that you can just interact with them digitally
and they certainly aren't configured in a way
which you can just establish provenance
for something off the bat.
In fact, we've seen instances where provenance
sort of gets reversed because somebody races
to the intellectual property system
to register ahead of the person who actually created it.
And so again, blockchains are a technology
for establishing immutable proof of provenance
with guaranteed interoperability.
And that makes them ideal for having public registries
and things like intellectual property
and then serving as the programmable layer.
My friends at Story Protocol,
one of our portfolio companies referred to programmable IP
that intellectual property should be directly accessible
to the programming of the software layer.
And that possibility is only just coming online
and it's awesome.
- What I love about your framing is the successive ways
that it zooms out.
It starts with me proof of personhood.
I wanna like bring my identity around.
So it starts with me, then it goes to us,
this sort of shared state concept
and then it goes to everybody.
Like a global kind of shared state.
- Exactly.
And then in math, we would say the dual.
The space around the space we just structured
are the guardrails around AI transactions and actions.
So I personally believe that we're gonna see
a huge marketplace of AIs interacting with AIs
without direct human oversight or supervision.
I don't know exactly how long it's gonna take to get there,
but you're gonna have an AI that's going out there.
I love Honkaku Mystery Novels.
- Yes, I know this from our reading lists
where you've recommended a few of them.
- Exactly. Like every reading list,
I have another Honkaku Mystery Novels.
Honkaku Mystery Novels,
they're these incredibly beautifully written
and very puzzling mystery novels from Japan.
The style is Orthodox.
Honkaku loosely translates to Orthodox
and they're 100% fair play.
Any clue that the detective sees you see.
And so it really is a puzzle.
You have to figure out, okay, with what I've seen,
how can I unravel this to explain the mystery?
I love these mysteries.
Every month or so, I scour the internet to see
which new ones have appeared in English translation.
I should have a bot.
I would love to have a bot just doing that for me.
Without me, they would just like order it for me.
Like, you know, if it finds one,
order it from whoever the publisher is,
have it shipped to me.
I would love to read it.
I've read as many of them as I can find.
- That's great.
You could preload your wallet, just give it a monthly allowance,
you know, 20 US stablecoins or whatever.
- And that's exactly it.
In order for this to work, I have to have confidence
that the AI understands the task,
that it can't be gained by somebody else creating like,
you know, honkaku.net where they just send blank pages
to steal my money.
And that the AI can't spend my entire bank account
if it discovers honkaku.net doesn't realize it's,
you know, not real and you know,
sort of buys like 10,000 copies of books or something.
And then I get this huge empty book box
and I'm thinking, wow, now there's a mystery.
In order for that to happen,
we need well-defined payment rails
and well-defined guard rails for these agents
to interact with each other
and sort of end commerce sites or end applications.
And that again is something
that blockchains are ideally positioned for
because they're about enabling you
to make immutable commitments
and make those commitments
part of the running of a software process.
You can basically tell an agent,
you have access just to this wallet,
you have access to just these memory areas
and you have these search instructions
that you can't go outside of
other than that, go find anything you can.
- I think that's a perfect note to leave off
on this stuff, need some rules of the road
and blockchains can provide it.
Great, thank you so much for joining us, Scott.
- Thank you, Q&E.
- All right, take care.
So Liz, it's actually perfect to have you on next.
We just spoke to Scott about some of his ideas,
including his last ones he was talking about,
sending an agent out to go do his shopping for him,
which seems like a pretty natural segue
into what you're writing about,
which is about how crypto in conjunction with AI agents
could potentially help solve this monetization issue
that the web is facing right now.
So let's hear from you, describe your idea.
- Yeah, so this came about through a number of conversations
that we have internally around what is the next generation
of the contract of the internet look like,
the original internet monetizing this idea of attention,
mostly, right?
So if you think about how Google came about and SEO
is all direct traffic to your website in return,
you let me surface your content on Google,
and this is kind of this fair exchange of sites
get more traffic and Google gets to make a lot of money
on advertising.
And so what does the next generation of that look like?
- And the reason that we need a next generation
is 'cause that model has basically collapsed now
with nobody needs to go visit websites anymore.
You can just get all the information you need
from an AI service or even Google
just putting the information up there
at the top of the webpage, their AI overviews,
I think they're called.
- Yes, exactly.
So you no longer need to actually go visit
the underlying site.
You can get these awesome summaries either through ChatchBT
or through Google's One Box or Proplexity
or whatever kind of tool you're using these days.
Because of that, you're kind of breaking
this economic contract of what is the purpose
of putting that information out into the world for free
as the underlying content site.
If you're not getting anything in return.
So how do you fix that?
And so I think there's a couple of different ways
you can approach this and different strategies
people are taking for how do you fix this monetization
and economic model if we're no longer directing people
to sites and how do you actually continue to incentivize
new content and the long tail of content on the internet
if we're breaking this economic model.
It might mean agents go out and just pay per data point
and they go out and as they need more context,
they pay for it.
The idea I walk through is this more fanciful idea
of what would it look like to do revenue sharing
through transactions.
In my view, people have gotten pretty accustomed
to the web being free and it seems unlikely
that they're willing to kind of fund these agents
to go do search for them when it would be free
for them to go to Google or it's free today
for them to use Google One Box or Proplexity
or these free versions of the agents.
And so if people aren't willing to spend money upfront
for the agent to pay for the data,
what else might this look like?
And so one idea that I just kind of walked through
is this idea of transaction sharing
between all the content sites and the end action.
So you send your agent out to shop for you.
If it actually ends up buying something,
there's some sort of revenue share back
to all the places that it got context for that.
- And by the way, it's cliche to say
that it's actually not free, you're paying with your data.
But despite that being cliche, it is extremely true.
The web which seems free is monetized.
It's just monetized in a way that you're not really seeing.
And so even if you're like,
oh, well, how are we going to add in all these transactions,
these payments and whatever,
the thing is all these ad networks have all of that
there already, it's just not in front of your face.
So it's not that radical a shift as one might imagine.
- Yeah, exactly.
Today you're basically doing this exact same flow
just with extra steps.
So you get served an ad when you go visit a content site,
the idea being that at some point you will convert
on that ad and actually go buy something.
And so the company is the ad agency,
the people advertising are willing to pay upfront
for that ad, assuming you will then convert
into a transaction.
The idea is to make that process more direct
given that we no longer have this attention
on the underlying site.
So instead of going to Google, getting routed to a site,
getting served an ad, possibly converting on that ad
and going and buying something later down the line,
that happens all kind of in at one flow through
of when that transaction occurs,
everyone involved in that transaction gets paid back
automatically.
And the great thing about that is that the attribution
is actually possible to trace because the agent
is pulling in context in real time.
And so it's not as kind of intangible as a human
who might visit a million sites and see a billboard
and see a friend talking about something
and trying to attribute back why they actually bought something
is a much more complex process than just attributing back
what the agent used in its path
to recommend to that end transaction.
- So what are the technical pieces
that need to be in place for this to happen?
- Yeah, so you need the ability to do
these very complex splits of nano payments,
which today is very challenging to impossible
given just the basic overhead
of a single credit card transaction
makes it infeasible to do these like a 10th of a cent
or 100th of a cent or 1000th of a cent transactions.
- And that's because there's just like a basic fee
on a credit card transaction.
I forget how much it is like 30 cents or something,
like which immediately gets rid of any opportunity
of doing anything beneath that cost point.
- Exactly.
And then you would also need to be able to do
this attribution of what data and context
is an agent pulling in.
And then you would just need a way to actually pay that out.
On crypto rails, this is as simple as putting in the metadata
wallet address that is paid out to every time you use the data,
you could even guard it or pay well in that way
just for agents to scrape it.
But in the traditional financial world,
this would be significantly harder to figure out
how to actually pay each content provider,
figure out a bank account or credit card number or
how you actually get that money back to them.
So yeah, needed ability to attribute where the data came from
to do these small and complex payment splits
and then actually be able to pay the underlying content creators.
- Do you think that we are going to get there in time
before AI eats all the good information
and sort of forces content creators to question
whether they wanna start publishing openly on the web?
- Yeah, I mean, I hope so.
I think it's definitely feasible.
It seems like today the direction we're mostly going in
is remaining with the agent as the intermediary.
So rather than you having this flow back effect
or this revenue sharing effect instead,
the agent companies like OpenAI or Anthropic or whoever
are paying directly for access to this data
through these big data deals with Reddit
or the New York Times or whoever.
So then you're paying your monthly subscription to OpenAI,
they're paying an annual subscription to the data provider
and then that data is surfaced in that agent
that does start to address this issue,
but going down that path ends up with this kind of
very siloed information where you're only gonna get
surfaced information on OpenAI with companies
and OpenAI has signed deals with
and you lose the openness of the web
and especially you lose the long tail
of individual content creators that can't get these
partnerships with OpenAI and so their information
is not surfaced the way that it might be today in Google
where even if it's not promoted
so it might not be on the first page,
you can still always find any data you want
and it kind of gives you this open access
that these information silos might not.
So it feels like we're heading more and more
in that direction, but hopefully we can make it
a little bit more fair and open.
- Excellent, while speaking of fair and open,
our website where you can read Liz
and the rest of these contributions is open,
not pay walled, so you can go read these posts there.
Liz, thanks so much for coming on
and sharing your idea.
- Awesome, thank you.
All right, Cara, so we just spoke to Liz
and she described her ideas for how AI agents
could be monetized potentially
or how content and data on the web
could continue to be monetized such that
like AI doesn't completely cannibalize the whole thing
and how crypto can potentially offer the ability to do
nano payments and other sorts of things
to prevent the web from, as Chris would say,
eating its own seed corn or corn seed,
or I don't know, some kind of farming reference seed corn,
okay.
- That's how you know he's from the Midwest.
- Exactly, yeah.
- Same.
- So this actually kind of meshes quite perfectly
with your contribution to the AI and crypto ideas list here,
which has to do with web crawlers.
I'll just set the context and say,
people hear the word AI agents
and the word might sound kind of funky and new and buzzy,
whatever, but like I love how you start off
by saying that web crawlers,
which have been around for decades now,
are a kind of first example of this,
like a primitive AI agent
that has existed on the web for a long time.
- Yeah, so the reason I started thinking about this
was because I did a panel last year on AI agent use cases
and at the time I said, you know,
the only AI agents that have real product market fit
are agents as entertainment and coding agents.
And then I started thinking about it a little bit further
after I left the stage and I was like, wait, I'm wrong.
Actually, the AI agent that has the best product market fit
is in any of these new things.
It's actually something that's been around
since the very genesis of the internet, so to speak,
which is the web crawler, which is an agent
that literally represent what we call a user agent,
autonomously navigates the web,
decides what data to collect, decides which links to follow,
which paths to bark down, and then comes back
and gathers that data on behalf of the user.
Today, nearly half of all internet traffic is non-human
and, you know, is representing a user agent
is like a bot or a web crawler.
- Wow, so the scales have tipped.
The web is now more bot, more automated than it is human.
- Yes, and that's why I say that this is the product
with the best product market fit is just because
the population, like if you were to take a census
of internet activity, like the users of CPU bandwidth
or like compute for website hosting,
the vast majority of it is coming from non-human sources,
is coming from these AI agents.
So whether or not you believe that to be product market fit,
the volume is sort of staggering.
It used to be the case that you would only use a crawler
for a small and constrained use case today.
Every single major company has an AI crawler,
whether it's Amazon using their crawlers
to track pricing for vendors who also sell
through their own channels in addition to
on the Amazon marketplace, or actually the most common crawler
if you check in the network activity tab of any web pages
is usually byte spider, which is TikTok's crawler,
which is feeding into the TikTok feeds
to decide what is relevant for the algorithm, yeah.
- So yeah, it's not just Google anymore.
There are crawlers all over the place.
That's so interesting that TikTok actually has
like the biggest crawler.
- Yes, yeah, they call it byte spider.
Every major internet company has a special little name
that is some derivative of their company name
to represent their user agent, web crawler.
And the point is like, okay, so why do these companies
want to crawl the web?
Well, Amazon wants to be able to penalize the merchants
on its site that charge a lower price
on their own first party platform.
So they will literally downrank vendors
that have their own first party sales channels
and give favorable pricing to their own channels.
And this is like a core part of how they design
their algorithms today.
Like their algorithms are not only trained
on this data that they crawl and search for,
but also use it as real time data to like up and downrank.
They use it as part of their rag,
which is retrieval augmented generation.
So they use it real time, both at inference time,
but then also in pre-training and post-training.
So this has now become a really important part.
I think there's this idea that the internet-scale data
that is accessible to common crawl is commoditized,
but it certainly is.
But it's also used at like every point in model generation,
both in the training and in the inference,
and at inference time.
So this is like a really important piece
of internet infrastructure.
And what's really interesting is like,
yes, the common crawl accessible data
is becoming commoditized, but it's also the case
that an input to this problem is that the surface area
of common crawl accessible content
or like crawl or accessible content
has contracted dramatically because there's no incentive
for creators to continue to supply that content
to crawlers for free.
And this was something that Chris and I wrote about
in our blog post about Story Protocol.
About a year ago, we hypothesized
that the social contract of the internet
was going to fall apart,
where creators are incentivized to provide their content
for free so that platforms can index
and then provide distribution back to them as a service.
That was like the original social contract of the internet.
Today, if the primary distribution engine
and the way information gets surfaced
is through LLMs, which do not provide attribution
back to those original content sources,
there's no incentive for creators
to provide that content for free.
So what you see is increasingly things are put
behind paywalls, but also you can see
in the open Cloudflare data that websites are choosing
to just block crawlers altogether.
Any crawler that is known to be associated
with like an AI user agent can be blocked in one click
on Cloudflare or any other posting provider.
And so about a year ago, only about 9%
of the top 10,000 websites were blocking AI crawlers.
Today, that number is around 37%.
And so, of course, the closer you get to the top 100 websites,
the numbers skew up dramatically
because content is their business, right?
So they're very aware of this fact.
And then if you go to the top million sites,
website owners are less proactive
about this kind of blocking activity
because they're just less savvy
or less concerned about this distribution problem.
- In the last era of the web,
there's been this sort of steady rise
of people adopting ad blockers,
but it sounds like in this current moment,
this shift that we are seeing now
into the AI sort of dominated web,
this throwing up paywalls and putting crawl blockers up
is happening much more quickly.
- Yes, and part of the reason this happens
is because of course, firms are more rational actors,
so to speak, like firms are very quick to respond
when they understand that the basis
of their business is being disrupted.
- Yeah, if it affects your bottom line, you're gonna notice.
- Yes, and firms are in general much quicker
to act rationally than consumers are
because they're very aware, you know,
they have people doing analysis
on what drives their bottom line.
Basically, all of this is to say,
I've been thinking about how we've arrived
at this sort of standstill.
We are entering this data constrained world
where it's not clear that models
will be able to continue improving at the rate
that they've been improving
because supply of non-commoditized data
and supply of common crawl accessible data
is becoming increasingly constrained
for all the reasons we've discussed.
So that's on one side of the standstill,
and then on the other side of the standstill,
it's like, okay, if we're getting all of our information
from LLMs, how do creators get distribution?
Or how do people who are creating original content
get attribution and get paid for providing the information
that these models were supposedly trained off of?
And I've been thinking, like, what if instead of,
you know, website owners paying CDNs to outright block anyone
who shows up and seems like they might be a bot,
we met somewhere in the middle where AI bots could pay
for the right to collect data in real time
as they're visiting all of these websites
and doing their crawling work.
And this is where blockchains come in.
In this scenario, every webcrawler agent could have
a little bit of crypto that they control,
and they might be able to engage in an on-chain negotiation
with the bouncer agent that represents a website.
And they might be able to do some sort of challenge
or transaction or negotiation and decide, okay,
this is like the auction price for collecting
this kind of data on our site today.
And you might be able to initiate that payment
through an open protocol like X402,
which was released by the Coinbase team
and is like perfect for this use case.
So that's the general idea.
It's a kind of lofty thing,
and it's going to be very challenging, of course,
because it requires a lot of different website owners
to buy in, right? And at the very least,
it will require CloudFlare or some big CDN
to get on board with this new standard,
which would essentially take the place
of the robots exclusion standard,
which is how webcrawlers get turned away today.
And that's how it's been since the '90s.
>> So what you're describing is basically
going from a world where we have these bespoke content
licensing partnerships between some AI company
and content provider, like say, a major newspaper or magazine
or something, where they strike a deal,
they give however many millions of dollars
and they get the content and return
to supply into their models.
Instead of that world where you have these bespoke arrangements,
you're talking about a world where you have a marketplace
that is designed specifically for agents to come on board
and negotiate these things in a more sort of automated way,
in a standardized and automated way,
rather than a bespoke and kind of like custom way
that we're seeing right now.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> I would maybe draw the analogy to say that
we've actually seen something like this on the web before.
Like the first banner ad was on hotwire.com, AT&T bought it
and that was the first display banner ad.
And then eventually from there,
we had the development of ad networks
that take care of all this thing in the background
at the blink of an eye.
It became standardized, professionalized.
And so maybe that is the exact sort of thing
we're going to see with AI agents moving forward.
>> Right, and you can generalize this
to be almost like an access control network
and not just a web crawler network.
'Cause I think one question emerges
like how do you decide whether somebody
is a bot or a real human?
Like that's a prerequisite to being able to enforce
this kind of standard or policy.
And one challenge is that crawlers can spoof themselves
as actual users.
They can say that they're Mozilla, X, Firefox.
They can pose as a user, as a real human on the internet.
And it can be very difficult to differentiate
between a bot that claims that it's a user
and an actual user.
You sort of rely on the integrity of the bot creator
to make a very helpful name like Bitespider
to identify itself, right?
I think the other thing is you would have to create
a multi lane highway to differentiate
between humans and bots.
And maybe the answer is that you just assume
everyone's a bot unless they have some session cookie
in their browser that says, this is Cara's world ID.
And this is how you know that's a human.
And it's also the case that you can imagine a world
in which you have an agentic browser
that has a notion of like who the user actually is
that has a sense of the user's identity.
And then you might actually have a whole cohort of agents
that you can delegate different fine grained access control
passes to.
So one might be Cara's authorized official representative
that has access to all my bank accounts
and can actually access websites as my user agent.
But I might also have Cara's spider
that is not an authorized representative of me
but has some money and can go pay to crawl
other people's websites.
- Well, as you mentioned at the start of this conversation,
the fact that more than half of internet traffic
is now generated by bots, it seems like it would make sense
to put the burden of proof on the user
to have to show that they are in fact human.
You might have to assume that everything is a bot
and then use some proof of personhood
to enable people to differentiate themselves.
- Right, the best case scenario is we get into this world
where everything is free for humans.
You know, information wants to be free, media wants to be free,
let that be free for real eyeballs.
And then everything is just extremely highly taxed
for bots that are either representatives of firms
and like have some sort of underlying economic incentive
or like economic subsidy, basically,
to go and browse the internet.
- Cara, thank you so much for your time.
I could not ask for a better layup
for our next conversation with Jay
where we're talking about proof of personhood.
So thank you also for that.
- I aim to please, that's my job.
It's almost like I work with these people.
- Incredible, all right.
Well, thank you, take care, Cara.
- Thanks, bye.
- All right, Jay, thanks for being with us.
- Yeah, of course.
- Okay, so we just got off the line with Cara
who is describing an internet
in which you've got a lane for humans
and a lane for bots potentially,
which kind of is the perfect setup
for your idea on the AI and crypto list,
which is about proof of personhood.
Tell us what you are putting forward.
- Yeah, of course, the context for what I wrote
and what Scott and I wrote is AI and generative AI
are mind-blowingly incredible but have massively increased
the cognitive overload of using today's internet.
So consumers are constantly worried,
is the person that I'm interacting with real
is the content that I'm consuming online real?
Is it coming from the person that I think it's coming from?
And products and services and companies
have to worry about protecting users' trust
and preserving valuable resources like compute or IP
or data or bandwidth or customer support.
And what we think the most credible solution to that
is proof of personhood,
which is a mechanism that enables anyone to prove
to another app or service or human
that they are a verifiably unique human being.
And what it does kind of like what Cara was mentioning
is it effectively divides the internet
into an internet with human beings and agents and bots
and an internet that is exclusively for human beings.
And where all the services and the apps and the protocols
on this side of the internet or this lane of the internet
is just humans.
And what's really exciting about that
is we have decentralized proof of personhood mechanisms,
like world's proof of human or world ID.
- Yeah, let's talk about this.
So world just launched in the US,
which is a pretty big deal.
And I think that's probably what people think of
when they think of proof of personhood.
They probably think of world ID first.
- When they think of decentralized proof of personhood
specifically.
- Yeah, okay, so tell us the difference.
- Decentralized proof of personhood is unique
and that it's fully censorship resistant.
It's secure, it's unstoppable.
It can't be taken down by a centralized party
or a government or entity.
It's incredibly neutral,
meaning it's fully transparent.
And there's not a gatekeeper that can discriminate
in how an ID is issued.
- Unlike a passport which potentially
you can get your passport taken away
or even if we want to extend the idea of identity
and talk about like a bank account,
you can get your bank account frozen.
And it can be denied, it can be frozen,
it can be deemed invalid by some service or entity.
And decentralized proof of personhood is incredibly neutral.
Beyond that, it enables permissionless accessibility
for developers or platforms.
There's no centralized party that controls the access
or approval or can block a certain use case or application.
And perhaps most importantly, it's self custodial,
which means in some cases it's privacy preserving
like world ID and then users have full control
over their identity data and have full autonomy over it as well.
- But your idea here, it's not just about proof of personhood,
it's about this idea of forward compatibility.
Maybe you could zero in on that
and explain what you mean there.
- Yeah, so forward compatibility
or I think it's also often called
like upwards compatibility means that the system can be updated
and still work properly with any applications or services
that want to work with that system or ID system.
- Okay, and that's important here because
that is important here because centralized identity systems
require an upgrade or update from a single party
that controls the data or stores the data, et cetera.
And so here it is fully trustless for both users
and developers and they don't have to think about
the maintenance costs or overhead that comes with
identity systems and the kind of centralized domain.
- Gotcha.
So people are probably pretty familiar
with what world is doing.
There was a Time Magazine story.
The orb was on the cover.
They've gotten pretty good coverage all over.
But who else is working on this idea?
Where else might people encounter it?
- There's another decentralized proof of personhood
startup called Self.
And then there's a kind of similar protocol
for verifiable credentials called the Solana Attestation
Service, which is really new.
And they allow issuers to associate information
like a KYC verification or geographic eligibility
or accreditation status with a user's wallet.
And so these attestations are signed, they're verifiable
and then users can take those across a number
of different applications without exposing any
of the sensitive data on chain or having to go through
these verification steps over and over again.
- Amazing.
And by the way, listeners, we just had Anatola Yaquavenko
on our podcast.
So you can check out that episode.
It's called The Inside Story of Solana.
Jay, anything else you wanna mention before we head on out?
- Yeah, I'd say what's probably most exciting about this
is that we are seeing a number of use cases
for decentralized proof of personhood pop up
both inside and outside of crypto.
I think inside of crypto, you see a lot of really cool
protocols like Morpho, which does lending,
offering exclusive lending rates to folks who are verified
with a world ID.
There's this kind of experiment around priority block space
for people who are verified, world ID holders.
And then outside of crypto, you have integrations
with Match Group, which allows them to add
this enhanced layer of trust for users
and verify that users are above 18
without revealing any sensitive information.
And you have integrations with Shopify
where Shopify merchants lose a ton of money
to bots that are stealing discounts
or people that are spinning up fake emails
to claim multiple discounts.
And they can offer discounts exclusively
to people that have a world ID.
So I think the acceleration of use cases
both inside and outside of crypto
is really, really exciting for proof of personhood.
- That's pretty awesome.
It sounds like there is going to be a fast lane
developed now maybe for humans.
And once the service that you're getting
is so much more convenient or useful or quick or whatever,
that seems like a pretty good road to adoption.
And you see that even at airports, you know?
I've got digital ID and breeze on past the security line
makes it quite a nice experience.
Jay, thanks so much for being here and sharing the idea.
- Thanks for having me on.
- Matt, hey, welcome.
So you are closing us out for our roundup
of AI and crypto related ideas.
I think we've all had the experience
of having creepy ads chase us around the web.
I recently visited a cavern
and now I'm getting cavern related content on Instagram.
So that's interesting.
Tell me what you mean by making ads personalized
and tailored but not creepy and how crypto
can in fact solve this problem.
- So I think it's actually best to take a step back
and to describe it in kind of two parts.
So if we're envisioning what's happening in the ecosystem,
in crypto, we're starting to get like really low fee
transactions, which basically mean money can flow really fast
as well as some digital identity systems.
So the ability to prove a person as a person.
- And we just talked about that with Jay, actually,
who was on right before you.
- Exactly, this is a little bit tangential to that,
which is the case of like,
what if we can start decentralizing
basically recommendation engines?
So with AI and AI agents,
especially with people trusting them,
can people either run their own
or have people run their own on their behalf
to kind of advocate for their own interests?
So instead of you receiving ads for caverns
because like you clicked on a cavern once,
it happens to just know that like,
hey, your car is getting kind of old
and you're looking for a new one.
And so it starts to like reach out,
find ads for cars you would like,
which are gonna be very specific and tailored to you.
And then starts to like, go to the ad people
and be like, hey, I'd love to serve this ad to this guy,
but how much will you pay me?
And by it, it means you.
- So that's a really fascinating inversion
on the way advertising works today.
You know, right now, basically you've got big companies
that have to make all these guesses about who you are
and what your needs might be based on your demographics
or what little information they can glean
about what kind of person you might be.
But what you're describing is like, okay, I have an agent
and that agent happens to know that I bought my Subaru
in like 2017.
And you know, it's got however many miles on it,
hundreds of thousands and it's about time
that we get an upgrade to a new car or something like that.
So it's this much more proactive kind of relationship
with ads and advertising that even gives users more agency.
- Yes, and then the crypto aspect of it is more or less,
there's a big problem with like self-attested demographics
and hey, this person will definitely love this ad
that is solved by identity, zero knowledge proofs
and then making it so they can actually pay you.
Cause like, to view an ad, no one's gonna hand you
like a hundred dollars usually.
They're gonna hand you to view an ad, you know,
maybe multiple cents.
And then like those transactions aren't feasible
with high fee systems.
Imagine trying to use a credit card to give someone like 10 cents.
The answer would be it would all go to the credit card company
and the issuing bank and the guy would receive nothing.
Or it would just be denied because I don't know
if they allow transactions under a dollar,
if we're being honest.
And so you get into these systems where like,
as they start to stack them, we could potentially have
a really cool future where you're able to make decisions
for yourself or rather you're able to get something
that can make decisions for you in your interest.
- So there's two parts of what you just said
that are really interesting.
One is the privacy aspect of it.
And the other is the sort of compensation
or monetary aspect of it.
So like from a privacy perspective, you know,
right now we live on a web where big corporations kind of
suck up all of our data and they become these giant honeypots
and like do they even want to deal with that data anyway?
It's kind of a liability.
So what if as a user you got to keep all that information
to yourself and selectively prove that you are this kind
of whatever person like on a need to know basis,
you're sort of not giving up all of your information
but you can prove aspects about yourself
that prove that you would be the right target
for a certain ad.
- Well, and you can prove like you've never viewed
the ad before and other like dumb things
that advertisers are going to want to happen
if they're going to like pay you as an individual
to view an ad.
They don't want to get scammed.
And so like this is triage against that as well.
So not only are you preserving your privacy
on like your preferences and the fact that you want
to new car and all these other things,
you're also telling them,
hey, I'm not ripping you off.
And so like it does two things at once.
And these two things are very important
for the advertisers trusting those systems
and for the user being able to trust
how those systems operate.
'Cause like if I had to go on chain
and like I have to state my name, my preferences,
everything about me, 'cause it's possible
you're going to need to state like income information.
Like they may want to know like, hey.
- Yeah, I mean, that's going to depend
on what kind of car I buy.
Am I buying a McLaren or am I buying Toyota?
- Right, Mercedes is going to want to know
like does this guy make enough money
for me to advertise to him?
And so like you don't want to post all that information
just in plain text on chain for everyone to see,
you want to be able to like take some federated identity
that assures them you're a person,
take some zero knowledge proofs that assure them,
hey, I'm in an income bracket where you'd want to advertise
to me, I'm likely to view or I'm likely to purchase it.
There's a whole bunch of things that I can attest to
that you don't know exactly what it is.
You've just written a set of rules that like,
these are the things in a person I want to advertise to.
And I say, I am that type of person.
And then they go, okay, cool, here's the ad.
- That's so interesting.
Yeah, so there's the privacy aspect,
but it actually also works in the favor of the advertiser
like you're saying where you want to make sure
that somebody isn't just binging ads,
watching the same ad over and over
and getting paid by the advertiser or company.
- Yeah, you don't want click farms.
Like click farms are toxic.
Like right now you have a bunch of people on phones
viewing ads to essentially steal money from platforms, right?
You don't want that.
How do you avoid it?
Can you prove you're a person?
Can you prove all these other things about you?
Like, okay, can you prove you've never seen this ad before?
All right, we're good.
Here's the ad, have fun, and here's 30 cents.
Go view your article now.
And then I think we should also talk about the third component
which is whether or not like web services start to embrace
that you could charge small amounts for viewing content.
So like instead of an ad service model
on a thing like YouTube,
the YouTube people could just be like,
hey, listen, pay me four cents
and I'll let you view the video
or pay me four cents after the first 30 seconds.
And they could get points where like,
if they get a million views,
that's four cents per view, like kind of fire.
- It sounds like such a small shift.
Like, oh, just a few cents, whatever, you know, to pay,
but it is such a radical departure
from the way things operate now.
- It probably won't happen with like the C platforms.
It'll probably be new platforms up and coming
that realize we can use different forms of monetization
to go forward.
They'll start to use them.
If they catch on, then other people will look at it
and be like, why aren't we using that?
That makes more sense.
And then kind of like roll that forward.
But yeah, a lot of this is like,
could it happen maybe?
Will it happen?
No one knows.
- This, while it sounds like it does sound
like a radical kind of difference
in the way these business models operate,
there's actually also a lot of similarity
because these ad networks are making small micro
sort of transactions happen on the back end
of a lot of websites and enabling this monetized,
open free web.
And so it's not like something like that
doesn't already exist.
It just sort of shifts around a little bit
who is providing the money to who.
- Right, and how much is being provided?
It's likely that any network that was able to get this going,
it's probably paying a lot more to creators
because creators can see, hey,
users are paying you four cents to view it.
Give me three and a half.
And like instead of a 50/50 split like YouTube has
or like a 60/40 or something weird,
it just becomes a very transparent game they're playing.
They know exactly how much is there.
They know exactly how much is on the table.
And they also don't have risk of getting demonetized
by advertisers.
'Cause like, I can't get demonetized
if the users are paying me directly
and like users will go seek out the ads
or their AIs will seek out the ads.
So they're not next to my content.
They're just within the ad networks
where the ad page you get when you open your browser
and it says, hey, your funds are low.
You wanna watch some ads and they're like, okay, fine.
And then it shows you a bunch of cool ads you get hyped
and then you're like on the internet having fun.
Matt, would you willingly go out
and watch ads for compensation?
Well, I mean, I'm not gonna go to an ad company
and ask for the ad and go through all that process.
But if there's a bespoke built-in process for the AI
that is helping me manage my life and online identity
to go and do that for me, yes.
Like if I open it up and I'm just like, man,
I haven't seen any ads in a while.
Like I know there's stuff I'm probably just not aware of.
Tell me what's out there that I should probably be buying.
And then it brings up an ad.
It's like, hey, did you see this cool new thing
that was there?
I was like, I didn't, thank you, AI.
And that's by the way, the utility of ads, right?
Like they're a good thing when served and managed well.
The first thing that comes to mind when I think of being paid
to watch ads, I picture the guy from a clockwork orange,
you know, undergoing the Letavico technique
with his like eyes being set open or watching a screen
where he tries to close his eyes and his room beeps at him.
Watch the ads, watch the ads.
But that's the more dystopian point is like,
we're going to get to the point where ads or ad companies
or places that are trying to get you to watch ads
so they can monetize the ad buys are just going to sit there
and be like, we've found ways to detect how people
and when people are watching ads, and we'll take over
your 3D devices, and if you look away,
we're just going to stop the ad and make you look at it, right?
Versus like, if it's something you want,
if it's something you need, if it's a movie
that you'll probably watch, if it's a game you want to play,
if it's things you'd want, but you're just generally
not aware of it, that's where like,
you don't really have to coerce anyone
to watch ads they want.
That's not a thing.
Like I think we're too used to the caustic ads
to realize that like, there are certain ads that hit
and you're like, man, awesome.
Like I just, I was unaware this was there,
I'm going to go do this right now.
- Yeah, it sounds like the ad economy can work for you
and it can do so through the unique combination
of AI and crypto.
It's a pretty nice vision of how these two technologies
can coincide and provide some pretty interesting value.
- Absolutely, yeah.
Let's make the cypher funk feature happen.
- Excellent, all right, Matt, thanks for coming on.
See ya.
- So everybody listening out there,
you can check out Matt's idea,
as well as all the other people you heard on this podcast,
if you go to a16zcrypto.com.
You can see their special feature called AI
and crypto crossovers.
Chalk full of good ideas in there,
let us know what you think when you read it.
Thanks for listening.
(upbeat music)